With all the legitimate concerns about AIDS and avian flu --
مع كل الاهتمام المبرر بالإيدز وأنفلونزا الطيور
and we'll hear about that from the
وسنسمع عن ذلك من
brilliant Dr. Brilliant later today --
الطبيب العبقري د/بريليانت
I want to talk about the other pandemic, which is
أود أن أتحدث عن الوباء الآخر، وهو
cardiovascular disease, diabetes, hypertension --
أمراض القلب والأوعية الدموية، والسكري، وارتفاع ضغط الدم
all of which are completely preventable for at
وجميعها يمكن تفاديها تماما على الأقل
least 95 percent of people
لـ 95 في المائة من الناس
just by changing diet and lifestyle.
فقط بتغيير نظامهم الغذائي واليومي
And what's happening is that there's a
وما يحدث هو
globalization of illness occurring, that people
عولمة الحالات المرضية، بسبب أن الناس
are starting to eat like us, and live like us, and
بدؤوا يأكلون مثلنا، ويحيون مثلنا، و
die like us. And in one generation, for example,
ويموتون مثلنا. وفي جيل واحد، على سبيل المثال
Asia's gone from having one of the lowest rates of
تحولت آسيا من أقل نسب
heart disease and obesity and diabetes to one
لأمراض القلب، والسمنة، والسكري إلى أحد
of the highest. And in Africa, cardiovascular disease
أعلى النسب. وفي أفريقيا، وفيات أمراض القلب والأوعية الدموية
equals the HIV and AIDS deaths
تعادل الإيدز
in most countries.
في معظم الدول
So there's a critical window of opportunity we
إذن توجد فترة زمنية حرجة علينا
have to make an important difference that can
صنع فرق هام ليتمكن من
affect the lives of literally millions of people,
التأثير على حياة ملايين البشر
and practice preventive medicine on a global
ونمارس الطب الوقائي على مستوى
scale.
علمي
Heart and blood vessel diseases still kill more
أمراض القلب والأوعية الدموية لا توال تقتل عددا أكبر
people -- not only in this country, but also
من البشر -- ليس في هذه دولة فحسب، ولكن
worldwide -- than everything else combined, and yet
عالميا -- من كل الأمور الأخرى مجموعة، ومع ذلك
it's completely preventable for almost everybody.
يمكن تجنبها تماما تقريبا للجميع
It's not only preventable; it's actually
ليس فقط تجنبها، ولكنها في الواقع
reversible. And for the last almost 29 years,
يمكن عكسها. وعلى مدر الـ 29 عام الماضية تقريبا
we've been able to show that by simply changing
تمكننا من إظهار بأن تغيير الغذاء ببساطة
diet and lifestyle, using these very high-tech,
ونمط المعيشة، باستخدام هذه الأدوات المتقدمة جدا
expensive, state-of-the-art measures to prove how
المكلفة، والأحدث على الإطلاق للقياس لإثبات مدى
powerful these very simple and low-tech and low-cost
قوة هذه الأمور البسيطة غير المكلفة
interventions can be like -- quantitative
للوقاية يمكن التكون. قياسات
arteriography, before and after a year, and
الشريان، قبل وبعد عام، و
cardiac PET scans.
صور مقاطع الشريان
We showed a few months ago -- we published the
أظهرنا منذ بضعة أشهر -- نشرنا
first study showing you can actually stop or
أول دراسة تظهر أنك تستطيع إيقاف
reverse the progression of prostate cancer by
أو عكس تقدم سرطان البروستاتا
making changes in diet and lifestyle, and 70 percent
بتغيير النظام الغذائي والمعيشي، و 70 في المائة
regression in the tumor growth, or inhibition of
تقلص في حجم الورم، أو إيقاف
the tumor growth, compared to only nine percent in the
نمو الورم، مقارنة بـ 9 في المائة فقط في
control group.
المجموعة الأخرى
And in the MRI and MR spectroscopy here, the
وفي المقطع الموضح
prostate tumor activity is shown in red -- you can
حركة ورم البروستاتا تظهر بالأحمر -- يمكنك
see it diminishing after a year.
رؤية التقلص بعد عام
Now there is an epidemic of obesity: two-thirds of
الآن يوجد وباء الوزن. ثلثي
adults and 15 percent of kids. What's really concerning
البالغين و 15 في المائة من الأطفال. المخيف فعلا
to me is that diabetes has increased 70 percent in the
بالنسبة لي هو أن السكري قد زاد 70 في المائة خلال
past 10 years, and this may be the first
الأعوام العشر الماضية، ولابد أن هذا أول
generation in which our kids live a shorter life
جيل يعيش فيه أطفالنا حياة أقصر
span than we do. That's pitiful, and it's
منا. ذلك مؤسف، كما أنه
preventable.
يمكن تجنبه
Now these are not election returns, these are the
هذه ليست نتائج انتخابية، إنهم
people -- the number of the people who are obese
البشر -- عدد الناس السمناء
by state, beginning in '85, '86, '87 -- these are
بالولاية، بدءا من 85، 86، 87 -- هذه من
from the CDC website -- '88, '89, '90, '91 -- you
موقع مركز التحكم بالأمراض -- 88، 89، 90، 91 -- حصلنا
get a new category -- '92, '93, '94, '95, '96,
على تصنيف جديد - 92، 93، 94، 95، 96
'97, '98, '99, 2000, 2001 -- it gets worse. We're
97، 98، 99، 2000،2001 -- تزداد سوءا. نحن
kind of devolving. (Laughter)
نتراجع نوعا ما
Now what can we do about this? Well, you know, the
الآن ماذا يمكننا أن نفعل لهذا الخصوص؟ في الواقع، تعلمون أن
diet that we've found that can reverse heart
النظام الذي وجدناه فعالا في عكس أمراض
disease and cancer is an Asian diet.
القلب والسرطان هو نظام آسيوي
But the people in Asia are starting to eat like we
ولكن الآسيويين بدؤوا يأكلون كما نأكل
are, which is why they're starting to get sick
وهو السبب وراء ظهور الأمراض لديهم
like we are.
كما هو الحال لدينا
So I've been working with a lot of the big food
لذا فقد عملت مع العديد من شركات الأطعمة
companies. They can make it fun and sexy and hip
الكبيرة. يمكنهم جعلها ممتعة، وحديثة
and crunchy and convenient to eat healthier foods,
ومقرمشة ومناسبة للأكل الصحي
like -- I chair the advisory boards to McDonald's,
مثلا -- أنا أرئس مجلس إستشاري لمكدونلدز
and PepsiCo, and ConAgra, and Safeway, and soon
و بيبسي، وكونآجرا، وسيفوي، وقريبا
Del Monte, and they're finding that it's good
ديل مونتي، وقد وجدوا أنه جيد
business.
للعمل
The salads that you see at McDonald's came from
السلطات التي تراها في مكدونالدز أتت من
the work -- they're going to have an Asian salad. At
العمل -- ستكون لديهم سلطة آسيوية
Pepsi, two-thirds of their revenue growth came
في بيبسي، ثلثي زيادة دخلهم أتت
from their better foods.
من أطعمتهم الأفضل
And so if we can do that, then we can free up
لذا إذا تمكنا من فعل ذلك، سنتمكن من تفريغ
resources for buying drugs that you really do need
الموارد لشراء الأدوية التي نحتاجها فعلا
for treating AIDS and HIV and malaria and for
لعلاج الإيدز والملا ريا
preventing avian flu. Thank you.
ولتجنب أنفلونزا الطيور. شكرا